Guide to the Seymour Mauskopf Papers, 1930-1993
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Seymour Mauskopf papers 1930-1993
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mauskopf, Seymour H.
10 linear feet Extent: 4408 Items
Duke University Professor of History. Materials and recordings used in preparation for Mauskopf's book, The Elusive Science, and other research on the history of parapsychology and psychical research. Also includes articles by Mauskopf and other historians, scientists, and psychologists.
mauskopfseymour
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Original audiovisual materials are closed to use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Seymour Mauskopf Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2005-2012.
Biographical Note
Seymour Mauskopf is a professor emeritus of history at Duke University. He earned an AB from Cornell in 1960 and a PhD from Princeton University in 1966. His research interests include intellectual history, particularly the history of science, ranging from chemistry and the allied sciences in the 18th and 19th centuries to the history of parapyschology and marginal sciences.
Collection Overview
Collection (107 items, dated 1972-1985) contains materials used in preparation for Mauskopf's book, The Elusive Science, co-authored with M.R. McVaugh. Included are audio cassettes, transcripts, and notes. Interviews are with J.B. and Louisa Rhine, B.F. Skinner, Gardner Murphy, J. Gaither Pratt, and other prominent psychologists. Five notebooks contain chiefly Mauskopf's notes on the council minutes of the Society for Psychical Research; and there is also a reel-to-reel tape of an interview with Mrs. K.M. Goldney.
Addition (05-071) (2000 items, 1.6 lin. ft.; dated 1930-1978 and undated) includes miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, and printed material produced by and related to J. B. Rhine and the Parapsychology Laboratory, collected by Mauskopf and McVaugh for The Elusive Science. Includes 11 black-and-white photographs, as well as files of note cards indexing portions of the correspondence files in the Parapsychology Laboratory Records. The addition is open to researchers.
Addition (11-193) (2200 items, 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 1930s-1990s) includes notes and research, including photocopies of primary documents, about the history of parapsychology and psychical research. The collection also contains some drafts or notes by Mauskopf about The Elusive Science, as well as other writings by him relating to the history of science. Also includes printed materials, miscellaneous correspondence, and articles by other historians, psychologists, and scientists.
Addition (2012) (8 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1990-1992 and undated) contains a folder of materials for the Science, Technology and Human Values Program steering committee, with program brochures, a list of symposium topics and courses, and one set of Mauskopf's committee meeting notes along with his notes on the budget.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Mauskopf, Seymour H.; Mauskopf, Seymour H.--Elusive Science; Parapsychology -- Research -- History; McVaugh, M.R. (Michael Rogers), 1938-; Murphy, Gardner, 1895-1979; Pratt, J. Gaither (Joseph Gaither), 1910-1979; Rhine, J.B. (Joseph Banks), 1895-1980; Rhine, Louisa E., 1891-1983; Skinner, B.E. (Burrhus Frederic), 1904-1990
Contents of Collection
- Original Accession, 1972-1985, (5 boxes)
  Collection (107 items, dated 1972-1985) contains materials used in preparation for Mauskopf's book, The Elusive Science, co-authored with M.R. McVaugh. Included are audio cassettes, transcripts, and notes. Interviews are with J.B. and Louisa Rhine, B.F. Skinner, Gardner Murphy, J. Gaither Pratt, and other prominent psychologists. Five notebooks contain chiefly Mauskopf's notes on the council minutes of the Society for Psychical Research; and there is also a reel-to-reel tape of an interview with Mrs. K.M. Goldney.
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. This accession has not been processed and no boxlist is available.
  - Preservation copies (Box 1)
  - Preservation copies (Box 2)
  - Use copies (Box 3)
  - Use copies (Box 4)
  - Unlabeled materials (Box 5)
- Accession (2005-0071), 1930-1978, (4 boxes)
  Addition (05-071) (2000 items, 1.6 lin. ft.; dated 1930-1978 and undated) includes miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, and printed material produced by and related to J. B. Rhine and the Parapsychology Laboratory, collected by Mauskopf and McVaugh for The Elusive Science. Includes 11 black-and-white photographs, as well as files of note cards indexing portions of the correspondence files in the Parapsychology Laboratory Records.
  - Accession (2005-0071) (Box 1-4)
- Accessions (2011-0193), (2012), 1930s-1990s, (2 boxes)
  Addition (11-193) (2200 items, 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 1930s-1990s) includes notes and research, including photocopies of primary documents, about the history of parapsychology and pyschical research. The collection also contains some drafts or notes by Mauskopf about The Elusive Science, as well as other writings by him relating to the history of science. Also includes printed materials, miscellaneous correspondence, and articles by other historians, pyschologists, and scientists.
  Addition (2012) (8 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1990-1992 and undated) contains a folder of materials for the Science, Technology and Human Values Program steering committee, with program brochures, a list of symposium topics and courses, and one set of Mauskopf's committee meeting notes along with his notes on the budget.
  - Research Materials
    - Interview notes: J.B. Rhine, Thouless, Murphy, etc. (Box 1)
    - Notebook, unlabeled, undated (Box 1)
    - Research on Gardner Murphy (Box 1)
    - Historical (general) materials (Box 1)
    - Primary research photocopies (Box 1)
    - Parapsychology: The Elusive Science drafts and notes (Box 1)
    - American Society for Pyschical Research research and histories, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence notes, 1932-1935 (Box 1)
    - American Society for Psychical Research primary sources (Box 1)
    - American Society for Pyschical Research notes (Box 1)
    - Research and correspondence on the Rhines and history of parapsychology, 1970s (Box 1)
    - Application for History of Parapsychology grants, 1970s (Box 1)
    - Chapter 5 photocopies and notecards (Box 1)
    - History of parapsychology research and primary sources (Box 1)
    - Multiple personality research articles (Box 1)
    - Parapsychology reprints, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Papers and Writings
    - American Society for Pyschical Research papers and presentations (Box 1)
    - History of Marginal Science talks, papers, and notes, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - The Elusive Science reviews (Box 1)
    - Notepads from writings, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Epilogue drafts (Box 2)
    - Articles by Mauskopf, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - History of Science Encyclopedia entries (Box 2)
  - Other Materials
    - Articles by others, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Monte Cooper senior thesis (Box 2)
    - Rhine Research Center (Box 2)
    - General correspondence on parapsychology, 1970s, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1980s-1990s (Box 2)
    - Acc. (2012) Science, Technology and Human Values Program steering committee, 1990-1992 and undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Volumes
    - Human Personality and its Survival of Bodily Death, by Frederic W.H. Myers, 1903 (2 volumes of 1954 reprint) (Box 2)
    - The Seybert Commission on Spiritualism, 1887 (Box 2)
    - Preliminary Studies of a Vaudeville Telepathist, 1937 (Box 2)
    - Parapsychology: Frontier Science of the Mind, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Statistical Methods and Scientific Inference, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Extra-sensory Perception After Sixty Years, 1940 (Box 2)